<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly and holsom preseruatyue against disperacio[n] at al times necessarye for the soule: but then chiefelye to be vsed and ministred when the deuil doth assault vs most fiersely, &amp; doth approcheth nieste.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838339</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838339</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2714</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09947)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2714)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1114:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly and holsom preseruatyue against disperacio[n] at al times necessarye for the soule: but then chiefelye to be vsed and ministred when the deuil doth assault vs most fiersely, &amp; doth approcheth nieste.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Wyllyam Copland, for Richard Kele],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.L.I. [1551]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Another edition of STC 20203.5 (published in 1548 with title: A godlye and holsome preseruatyue against desperacio[n].).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A preseruatiue agaynst desperacion.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from STC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2714:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2714:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A godly and holſom preſeruatyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at al times neceſſarye for the ſoule: but then chiefelye to be vſed and miniſtred when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil doth aſſault vs moſt fierſely, &amp; deth appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſte.</p>
            <q>Be ſobre, and watch, for your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarye the deuell as a roring lyon: walketh about, ſeking whom he may deuoure, whom reſyſte, ſtedfaſt in the fayth <bibl>1 Pet. 5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>M.D.L.I.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2714:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2714:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hys preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue (ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der) is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure maiſt choſe oute ſuche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſentences as may bothe ſtaye thi owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacion: &amp; alſo quiet othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deuil ſhalbe buſie with them.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2</note> For we be not ignoraunte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoughtes of ſatan, howe he continually furniſheth hym ſelfe to bende his ordinaunce agaynſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And now w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greatnes &amp; multitude of ſyn Now with the terrour of death &amp; dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Ephe. 6</note> do labour to beate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buck let of fayth out of our han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,<note place="margin">1. Teſſ. 5</note> to ſtrike y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helmet of hope fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our head.<note place="margin">Ephr. 6</note> And to wreſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs the ſwerd of the ſpriit, which is gods word</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2714:3"/>
            <p>But here chriſtyan reader is thy ſwerd and buckeler deliuered vnto the, here is thy helmete put vppon thy heade here thou ſhalte find ſuche armoure and weapon, wherbi thou ſhalt both be able to withſtand the force of oure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men enemy the Deuell: and alſo (by the counſell) to reſcue others that they peryſh not, Yea heare y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt find choiſe of moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſentences, wherby mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience may be ſtayed from damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable deſperacion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.</note>Watche therfore, ſtand ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte in faithe, play the man, and be of good comfort.<note place="margin">Iacob. 4.</note> Reſiſt the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell, and he wyll flee frome the Not for feare of thy owne power ſtrength or holynes: but for feare of Chryſte: in whome by faythe thou art ingraffed,. For it is criſt through whome god hathe geuen<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 15.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2714:3"/> vs vyctory agaynſt ſynne, deathe hell, &amp; the deuyll.<note place="margin">Acto. 4.</note> Nether is there ani other name vnder heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geuen vnto man wherin we maye be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but the name of Ieſus Chriſt our lorde. To whome with the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and holye ghoſt, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory. AMEN</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2714:4"/>
            <head>A prſeruatiue</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orſomuche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſeaſes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy and corporall deathe, dothe ſo trouble mannes mynde, that we commonly trimble and quake at the onely mencyon of them: How much ought we to feare the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſoule and death of the ſame, then whiche, there can no greater nor more fearefull cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytye chaunce vnto man.</p>
            <p>And ſeinge that euery man doth auoyde (ſo muche as in hym ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ethe) the payne, myſeryes, dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and deathe of the bodye: howe much more ought we to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cline and eſchewe, the cauſes of theſe euilles, which be ſinnes and offences, and feare the ire of god, which we ſo (by oure enormities) do prouoke. Yf we be neuer ſo ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:2714:4"/> ſick in our body, by and by we ſend for the phiſycion, we ſpare no coſt we ſike for medecines and remedy, thoughe they be neuer ſo chargable, &amp; al to patch and clout vp this earthen v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſell of oure bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye. which do we neuer ſo muche can not laſt long. And why vſe we not lyke dylygence in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring &amp; ſeking remedies againſt the diſeaſes of the ſoule whyche like as thei be more greuous eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo they bring with them (without compariſon) infinitely more dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. For what can it profit a man thoughe he haue all the riches in the world, though he liue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yere, and that in ſuch health &amp; pleaſure, that he is not ones tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched with ſickenes or gryefe: hys ſoule in the meane time being poi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoned with ſinne being captiue to ſatan, hauing God diſpleaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2714:5"/> him, and dampnacion readye for him after thys lyfe. For truelye thys lyfe muſt once haue an ende nether know we whan, where, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what maner,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> or how ſone.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſayth Chriſt watch for ye nether know the day nor hour when the ſonne of man wyl come And leſt we this ſhorttime of our abode (omittinge thinges mooſte waightye and profitable) ſhulde folow trifulles, &amp; things of ſmal price: he hathe voucheſafe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vs an order and as it were a breue, certaine and ſure way: to come vnto true felicite ſayeng. Seke firſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of god and righteouſnes therof:<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> and all thynges ſhalbe added vnto you. Care for liuing, care for ryches, care for worldly dignytie, world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fauoure, worldlye eſtimacion and ſuch lyke tranſitory thinges
<pb facs="tcp:2714:5"/> which in dede doth lytle profitte but many times be cauſe bothe of filthy vices and alſo of greuous calameties (doth beſy, doth vexe doth trouble, doth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defatigat vs both day and nyght but in ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king for and procurynge of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; heuenly thinges: we be moſt negligent, moſt ſlacke, moſt dull moſt forgetfull. And I pray you what can be a greter blindnes or a more dangerous madnes? why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les we be luſtye, whyles we be in helthe, whyles we be in proſperity we ſcaſelye thinke vpon any lyfe to come we remembre not once y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall dye, But when we be in perell, and daunger by ſyckenes, and deathe begynneth to knocke at our dore. Euen at that ſame houre when we ſhulde playe the menne and fyght agnynſt our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimy, being ſufficiently armed &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2714:6"/> weponed afore) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begin we firſt to thinke vpon oure armoure to thinke vpon our wepon, to think vpon mending of our lyfe. Theſe thinges declare vs to be ſmallye exerciſed ſoudiers to be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſterous iudgement, and verye weaklings in fayth. God be mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyfull vnto vs. Amen</p>
            <p>But yet though a man be neuer ſo old though the day be neuer ſo far paſt, ſo he amend whiles he is here, eare it be night, his repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce cometh not out of ſeaſon, Neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theles it were to be wiſhed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no man ſhuld differ his repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance to his laſt &amp; moſt dangerous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſhal haue much ado to ſtand and to defend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues from the aſſaultes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> guiles, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſions of the enemy whych in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of their helth prepared &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them ſelues, what then ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:2714:6"/> come of them whiche not fearing god neither minding once repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce hath led a diſſolute filthie and naughty lyfe? how ſhal thei fyghte? howe ſhal they be able to wythſtand the force of ſatan?</p>
            <p>¶ Seinge therfore the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people is great, and the miniſters of the goſpel very few nether able to be euerye where to do their office to euery man: I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing a wil to help al men: haue gathered to gether, &amp; written out of ſcriptur, a certaine brief forme how to admoniſhe, inſtructe, and comfort ſuch as be ſicke, that thei either reding theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, or hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring them red bi others: may con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue certaine hope &amp; perfit conſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſt in this moſt dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict they faint, geue ouer like cowards, &amp; ſo be ouercomed &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſh: For this is certain, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a man is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> extreme ſick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:2714:7"/> &amp; is in daunger of deth, he is aſſauted with diuers many, &amp; gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous tentacions. Firſt it is a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and vehemente tentacyon, when he ſeeth the moſte terrible i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of deathe afore hys eyes, when he ſeeth he muſt leaue thys light, leue this life, leue frendes, leaue landes, goodes, kynfolkes father, mother, wyfe, childern, all thinges wherin he had here ether pleaſure or comforte. Then ſuch ſynnes as be againſt the wil and pleaſure of god hathe committed ſhall ſhewe and preſent them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and ſhall appere more in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, and more greuous then euer they ſemed afore, and ſo ſhal won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derouſly vexe and torment the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience. Then death, iudgemente, hell, dampnacyon as it were in a plumpe, ſhal aſſault and lay ſege with diuers daungerous engens
<pb facs="tcp:2714:7"/> agaynſt the old man of ours.</p>
            <p>In theſe Agonies, except a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be armed with a ſure and conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t faith: it is to be feared, leſte he be weried, tired and at laſt ouercom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med. For theſe tentacious whych chaunce vnto men lyeng in extre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes: appeare moſt houge fearful and daungerouſe, and that for bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe our fayth is verye ſlender, and waueringe, nyether yet able to ſee, perceaue or apprehend, the incomprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyble and ineſtimable riches of the children of god, why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che be remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes through Chriſt, reſurreccion of the fleſhe, communion of ſaynctes, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life and all theſe geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in Chriſt and for Chryſt.</p>
            <p>In theſe articles of our fayth we muſt dayly exercyſe our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Theſe we muſt diligentli reuolue and earneſtly expend in our min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.
<pb facs="tcp:2714:8"/> For thoughe all the artycles of our fayth are diligentlye to be remembred and without al waue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringe beleued: yet in the Agonye and poynte of deathe theſe foure (that is) the communion of ſaync<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, remiſſion of ſinne, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of Chriſte, the reſurrection of the fleſhe, and euerlaſtinge lyfe: are chiefely to be mynded expended, and inculcated.</p>
            <p>For like as deth is the paine &amp; ſtipend of ſinne:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> euen ſo for ſinne God dothe commenly puniſh vs with diuers diſeaſes and plages, As it is to be ſene i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers places of ſcryptur. Io. v. Pſa. 88. Deut xxviii.ii. Reg. xxiiii</p>
            <p>Neuertheles afflictions be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny tymes layd vpon vs that our fayth may be tried: For than is it eaſy to be perceaued howe much we loue GOD, what faythe we
<pb facs="tcp:2714:8"/> haue in him, howe we truſt hym, when we be preſſed &amp; greuyd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aduerſytie. In this caſe therfore we muſt bewayle &amp; acknowledge our ſinnes for the which we haue iuſtlye incured Goddes diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and deſerued moſt greuous paine, We muſt turne to god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true repentaunce in all our harte &amp; mynde withoute all faynynge and conterfating, we muſte haue recourſe vnto the Goſpell where we ſhall fynd moſt bountiful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i, abſolucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or remiſſio of our ſinnes which chriſt hath inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuted i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche Io. xx, Receaue (ſayth Chriſte) the holye ghooſte whoſe ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ye forgiue thei ar for geuen. This ineſtimable treaſur is dayly opened &amp; offred vnto vs Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remiſſion of ſinnes is thus deſire, &amp; optayned: vndoutedly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paine of ſinne which is the
<pb facs="tcp:2714:9"/> diſeaſe or affliccion ſhall ſone ceaſſe and leaue vs, or elles accordinge to the moſt beneficiall will of our heuenly father: ſhall turne to the profit and ſoule helth of him that is diſeaſed or afflicted, For this maye we be ſure of, that the paine and affliccion in the body in this worlde (ſeme it n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer ſo greuous a bourden or heauye yoke to the fleſh) as comenlye nothinge elles but a fatherly rod, wherwyth god doth drawe vs his children from ſynne,<note place="margin">Pſal. 88.</note> and call vs home to hym, Truly our heuynly father dothe loue vs moſte feruentlye, he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs good mynde,<note place="margin">Heb. xii.</note> and dothe all thinges, for our amendmente and profit for whome GOD lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uethe, him he chaſtiſethe, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectythe vs temporally here:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 11.</note> that we ſhuld not be puniſhed in hell euerlaſtingly. Thoughe he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mith
<pb facs="tcp:2714:9"/> angrie: he louith ſinguler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. Nether is his Ire the Ire of a tiraunt or torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tour deſirynge our perdycion: but of a father <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement and ſauftly Firſt therfore we muſte crye God mercy deſire pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; forgeuenes of our ſinnes (but by Chryſt, but with a hart truely penetente) that we may be at one wyth God and haue him merciful vnto vs This done we may then deſyre GOD to deliuer vs from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Imminente and preſent affliction and diſeaſe For ſo teacheth eccleſiaſt.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Sonne in thy infermitye neglecte not thy ſelfe, but pray to the lorde: and he ſhall delyuer the. Alſo in the Pſ.<note place="margin">Pſal. 70</note> remembre not o lord god our old iniquites but let thy mercye ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely preuent vs: for we be verye miſerable, helpe vs God oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. Lord God of power turne
<pb facs="tcp:2714:10"/> vs howe longe wilte thou be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie? ſhewe thy face and we ſhall be ſaued, Here we be taught fyrſt to deſire remyſſion of ſynne that we may ſo be at one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God: and after that to haue his wrathe, and the tokens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame taken awai. But when ſo euer we deſire to be deliuered or to be eaſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe that preſſeth vs we muſt alwaye annexe this addicion.<note place="margin">Mar. vi</note> Thy wyll (o heuenlye father) be fulfylled. Neither knowe we ſo well what is profytable vnto vs. Nether ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſo well prouide for our ſelues as our moſt louing heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father Which is both of infinite powre and alſo of incomprihenſible wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome whyche neuer turneth hys eys from vs, whiche carieth conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nually for vs wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch knoweth the numbre of our yeres, whych doth quicken, noriſh, fede, kepe, defend
<pb facs="tcp:2714:10"/> prouide for al his creatures much beter then thei can wiſh or deſire. But to drawe to the more perticu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler temptacions, &amp; to ſhewe what thinges do moſt fierlly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> daunge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rouſly at the time of deth aſſault vs. And how we ſhal w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ There be thre thinges, whych at the houre of death doth wonderouſly vexe trouble, &amp; feare our mindes (that is to ſaye) ſynne, death hell or dampnacion.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Syne</head>
                  <p>WHerten we haue vngodlye myſpent our life, wherby we haue greuoſly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded God and our neighbour: This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng to oure remembraunce when we lye vpon our death bed, doth dryue vs to a wonderous feare,<note place="margin">Rom. ii</note> penſiue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and anxiety. As ſainct paule ſayth, wrath indignacion to trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and anguiſhe agaynſt euerye loule of man that doth euell.</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:2714:11"/>
                     <head>¶ A medicine agaynſt ſynne vexinge and troublynge our conſcience.</head>
                     <p>LEt vs call earneſtly to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that the ſonne of god came downe from heuen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came man, toke vp on his backe the ſynnes of the worlde, died for them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, there makynge ſatiſfaction for vs and paing our dettes. This moſt precyous blod of chriſte was ſhed alſo for vs, &amp; of this death we be alſo partakers ſo we ryght lye beleue in Chryſte Nether nede we to doubt but Chryſte died aſwell for vs, as for Peter and Paule:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> For we be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed alſo (as ſaynct Paule ſayth) in the deth of chryſt. Thys ought to comfort, vs this ought to erect and ſtay our myndes. For ſeinge we be baptiſed in the deathe of chryſte, Chiſtes deathe bryngethe
<pb facs="tcp:2714:11"/> alſo vnto vs helth and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By Chryſts deth we be alſo dead to ſynne: by Chryſtes deathe we haue alſo certaine and ſure remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of our ſynnes, by chryſtes deth we be raiſed alſo to a newe and euerlaſtynge lyfe. For bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme is a couenand betwixt god and vs. And a ſygne of his grace and fauour towarde vs wherin we be reconciled and made at one wyth god againe, ſo that we may nowe haue a ioyfull and quiet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience, for ſomuch as our ſinnes be forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs through the reſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection of Ieſus chryſt, yea chriſt alſo in the inſtitucion of the moſt bleſed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his laſt ſupper ſpeaketh alſo to vs ſaynge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys bloud is ſhed for the remiſſion of ſynne. Nowe although we haue not liued alwaye innocentlye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther led ſuche a lyfe as we ought
<pb facs="tcp:2714:12"/> to haue done: Yet we maye not diſpaire, but without delay reſort vnto god, by true repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, cal faithfully vpon hys name, and we ſhalbe ſaued.<note place="margin">Rom. x</note> Ye let euery one of vs with a meke harte burſt out into theſe, or like wordes and ſay O moſt mercyful god, father of al mercy, father of oure LORD Ieſu Chryſte, be mercyfull vnto me a wretched ſynner, make ſpede to deliuer me, for the moſte bitter (but mooſt precious) death, and paſſion of Ieſu Chryſte thy only begotten ſonne, our redemer, and only ſauioure: Amen. Enter not (o lord) into iudgement wyth thy ſeruaunte, handle me not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to my deſeruyng, neyther do vnto me after my iniquities: but according to thy infinite and botomles goodnes &amp; mercye take me vnto the. I a miſerable and
<pb facs="tcp:2714:12"/> wretched creature am in thy hand I am in thy debt &amp; daunger thou mayſt do with me what it pleaſe the. O mooſt mercyfull father forſake me not, nor caſte me of. I am thine all that I am, There can no man comfort, no man help no man delyuer me, but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> alone. Thou art the true comforte, the moſt preſent helpe the ſureſt bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke in all neceſſite. Thou god art my refuge, my ſtrengthe, my helpe in al troubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Thou art my Lord in thy handes reſteth al my chaunce and affaires. Shew thy louinge and mercifull face vpon thy ſeruant, ſaue me in thy mercy O lord: but many wayes in our extreme ſicknes and affliction let vs beware we loke not to earneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly nether to longe vpon oure ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But rather let vs haue the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Chriſtes moſte helthfull
<pb facs="tcp:2714:13"/> and precious deth before our eys. Let vs fix that in our mynd and be full perſwaded that Chriſte is now bourdened with his ſynnes, that he hathe nowe taken theym vpon his owne ſhoulders and ſo hath ſatiſfied for theim and waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed them awai that he wil neuer charge vs with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but frelye for geaue vs theim as we profeſſe in our Crede, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſai Credimus remiſſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccatorum, we beleue the remiſſion of ſynnes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>¶ Here it ſhalbe mete that in our ſyckenes we call to remembraunce ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of holy ſcripture as teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fieth of remiſſion of ſynne purchaſed by Chriſte of the which ſome be here ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. i.</note>BEhold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of God which takith away the ſynne of the worlde.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2714:13"/>
                     <p>We are bought with no golde nor ſiluer,<note place="margin">i. Pet. i</note> nether any corruptible price, but with the precious bloud of the vnſpotted and vndefyled lambe Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>¶ So god hath loued the world that he gaue hys onely begotten ſonne to the ende that we ſo bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge in hym dothe not peryſhe but haue lyfe euerlaſting<note place="margin">Io. iii</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>I come not to call the righteous but the ſinners to repentaunce.<note place="margin">Mat. ix</note> Come vnto me all ye that labour and are laden and I ſhall refreſh you, Lo he calleth all,<note place="margin">Mat. xi</note> he refuſeth he excludeth none, we muſt includ alſo our ſelues within his words</p>
                     <p>All we muſt reſorte to him, and he wil receaue and reffeſhe vs,</p>
                     <p>God ſetteth forth hys loue to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward vs: For Chriſt died for vs,<note place="margin">Rom. v</note> when we were yet ſinners, muche more now therfore we being iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="tcp:2714:14"/> bi his blood ſhalbe ſauffe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrath by him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Cor. i</note>Chriſt Ieſus is be commed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs wiſdom, righteouſnes, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> though we haue be neuer ſo gret ſinners, let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe and knowledg our ſynne let vs call for mercye and pardon, let vs vnfainedly beleue chriſt to be our only helth Iuſtice, and rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t on: and ſtrayght waye he is ſo, he wyl by and by couer and put awai our ſinnes in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhal nede fere no peril nor dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">ii. Cor. v</note>Him that knew no ſinne, hath god made ſinne .i. a payment of ſinne for vs, that we ſhuld beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the righteouſnes of god by hym.<note place="margin">Gal. i</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſt gaue him ſelfe for our ſinnes that he myghte delyuer vs fro this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wicked world acor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the wil of god our father</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2714:14"/>
                     <p>In Chriſt we haue redemption throughe hys bloude,<note place="margin">Ephe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> euen the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſion of ſynnes according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riches of his grace.</p>
                     <p>Chriſt Ieſus is come in to this world to ſaue ſynners<note place="margin">i. Tit. i</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſte Ieſus hathe geuen hym ſelfe a redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">i. Tit, ii</note> This let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly beleue vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted we be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nombre of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe ſaued. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is come a redemption for all, theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hath ſuffered pertayneth no leſſe to the &amp; me &amp; euery one of vs (ſo we beleue) than to Peter or Paule Chriſt hath borne our ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in his body vpon the croſſe.<note place="margin">i. Pet. ii</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſt died ones for our ſynnes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghteous for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnrighteous.<note place="margin">i. Pe.. ii.</note> The bloud of Ieſus chryſt clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs from all ſinne.<note place="margin">i. Ioan. i</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>If ani man doth ſinne we haue a aduocate w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus<note place="margin">i. Ioan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2714:15"/> Chryſt the ryghteouſe and he is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> attonemente for our ſynnes: Not for ours onely: but for the ſynnes of the whole worlde.</p>
                     <p>By theſe places and ſuche lyke we maye ſe howe god the father (which wyll not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, but that we ſhulde turne and lyue) for that mooſt feruente bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng loue that he beareth toward vs hath eaſed vs of the burden of our ſin, &amp; hath layd it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> back of his moſt dere beloued ſonne. which his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne hath ſo take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, borne and ſuffered for them: that they can neuer condemne vs. For god taketh and reputeth the deathe of his ſonne for a full ſatiſfactyon &amp; paiment for al our ſinnes, ſo that we truly beleue in hym: For ſeing that our ſinnes thus layde vpon Chryſt could not ouercome hym, retain him in deth, nor da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne him
<pb facs="tcp:2714:15"/> (for why he roſe againe) vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly a full ſatiſfaccion is alredye made for them, the iuſtyce of god is fully anſwered, and they be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly hid and forgeuen. Let vs be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue thys and we ſhall not peryſh euerlaſtingly. For chryſt is nowe become ours, with al that he hath with hys death, with hys reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, wyth his aſſencion into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, with his lyfe,<note place="margin">Qui pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio filio ſuo non ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percit.</note> his merites hys glorye. As ſaynt Paule wytneſſe. Rom. viii. wherfore Satan hath nowe no title to vs, he can not me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle with vs, he hathe no power to hurt vs. Forſomuch as we be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by chriſt purged from our ſynnes and made the chyldren of god by Chryſt who hath reconcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs &amp; wrought our peace, we muſt therfore be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte. For ſeinge we be in the handes of god, that is omnipotent, who is
<pb facs="tcp:2714:16"/> now our beſt moſt loui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; truſty father we be in a ſureporte, we be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, there ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity nor aduerſitie hurt vs for we be inuironed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cuſtodi of god &amp; the gard of angels, oute of the handes of this heuenly father can no creature by force pluck vs When we be at an end by deathe of thys croſſe and corporal aflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then haue we ended our iour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney, then ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e we fynyſhed oure warre: Chriſt hathe borne the ſame croſſe Chryſte hathe paſſed the ſame waye, he hathe ſuffered lyke deathe, he is oure heade we muſt be lyke to hym we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fre with hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf we intend to raygn with him we muſt leue thys cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall lyfe ere that we can enioye lyfe euerlaſting. Lette not oure ſinnes trouble vs: lette them not tormente oure conſcyence, as
<pb facs="tcp:2714:16"/> though they coulde not be forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. They are alredy forgeuen, if we repent and beleue: Chriſt is al ours as muche as he is. He by hys innocency hath couered and taken away our ſynnes. As Chryſt can not be dampned, euen ſo we can not be dampned, yf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ryghte faythe, we cleaue vnto hym. As ſynne, deathe, and hell, hadde no power agaynſt Chryſte ſo haue thei no power againſt vs ſo we be in Chryſte, and Chryſte in vs. Yf the matter hadde be left and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to vs to haue borne our owne ſinnes and to haue ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied for them, they wolde haue be to heuy for vs, we had not be able to ſtande vnder theym they wold haue preſſed and ſunke vs downe to hell. But chriſte bothe god and man hathe (of hys owne
<pb facs="tcp:2714:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> free will) offered hym ſelfe for vs. he hath taken our turne, he hathe playd our parte, and paide for vs all that we ought. As it is in the Pſalme ſpoken in the perſone of chriſt, I payd that I oughte not, We had treſpaſed, we were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> det<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo farre behind hand, that all that was in vs, was not able to paie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſt ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me we ought. Chriſt became our ſuerty, paid for vs ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quited vs, and ſet vs at libertie yea, made vs coheires wyth hym of euerlaſting glorye</p>
                     <p>If it were poſſible for one man to commit the ſinnes of the whole worlde, ſo he truelye repente and cleaue by true fayth to Chryſt he can not be dampned, hys ſynnes be ſufficiently and abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly by Chriſt ſatiſfied for. For Chryſt (as touching hys godhead one in ſubſtance with the heuenly father
<pb facs="tcp:2714:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> As touchynge his man hede oure very fleſh and bloode (hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed and truely boughte grace and pardon for vs. For Chryſt be came man for vs, was borne for vs died vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe for vs, roſe from death for vs, aſcended into heuen for vs, and hath accomply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and perfourmed all thynges mete for our ſaluacion for vs. If therfore we beleue in chriſt we are beco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e partakers of Gods fauor we are eaſed of the packe &amp; bourde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne, we are made the heires of god and coheiris with Chryſt for euer, and that by chryſte and for chriſt. For withoute Chriſt there is no conſolacion on helth no hope no helpe. In Chryſte alone is all comforte, all helthe, all hope, all ſuccoure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all refuge all grace and mercy more habundant more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, more excele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t than any man
<pb facs="tcp:2714:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> is able either to comprehend or to wiſhe. God graunte vs therfore a true and a conſtant faith. In this forme or in like ſort we moſt com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort our ſelues in our ſickenes or calamitye, and our brother beinge viſited. But in ani wais and with al dilygence it is to be foreſeene, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wythdrawe oure mynde from the fearefull and terryble contem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>placyon of ſynne, death, and dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacyon. And that we fixe theſe of our mynd and whole thoughte v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon chriſte onlye, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we cleue vnto him, that we call vpon hym, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit our ſelf wholy to hym. For in chriſt we ſhal eſpie nothng but innocencie, iuſtice, lyfe, ſaluacyon which al be deriued from Chryſte into vs, ſo that we wyll acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, &amp; receaue him for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thor of our ſaluacion and only re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demer, yf we haue chriſt crucified afore our eyes: if we imprinte him
<pb facs="tcp:2714:18"/> in our hart, yf we flee to hym with out fath: if we wholy clyue to him Then ſhal hel gates nothyng pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayle againſt vs, then ſhal we be able to wythſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d al the forcible aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaultes of Satan, though thei be neuer ſo ſore, neuer ſo fierce, neuer ſo terrible.</p>
                     <p>Let vs cal to remembraunce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what lenitie, what ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilnes, what humanitie, what clemency Chryſt (as it is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euangelicall hiſtory) hath called vnto him and receued al ſuche ſinners as hath repented them and deſired his helpe. We ſhall finde Mary Magdalen, the ſynner that honge vpon the right hand of chriſt crucified, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licane, zache, wyth other mo who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Chryſt moſt louyngly receiuinge pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced cleare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, (though they had ſynned greatlye) and the chyldern of ſaluacion, chryſte is
<pb facs="tcp:2714:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> very grace, mercy, helpe, comfort, life, ioye, and ſaluacion to al thoſe which loke for theſe things at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des: and put theyr truſt in hym And all theſe thynges hathe God (who is truethe it ſelfe &amp; can not lie nor wyl not deceyue) promyſed vnto vs for chryſtes ſake.</p>
                     <p>Fynallye whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deth approcheth we muſt do as Chryſte dyd vpon the croſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. vi</note> we muſt praye for our enemyes and forgeaue them with our harte. Yf we haue offended any man we muſt be hartely ſory for it, we muſt deſire forgeuenes. yf we haue iniured anye man, we muſt make hym amendes, or take ſuch order that amendes maye he made vnto him, yf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t paſſeth oure power to make reſtytucyon and amendes: it ſhalbe ynoughe that we deſire forgeuenes. And wyth our hartes forgeaue others which
<pb facs="tcp:2714:19"/> hath hurt vs ether 11. name, body ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ance or eſtimacion. For if we truely forgeue: god hathe promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed we ſhalbe fyrgeuen as it is in the ſyxt of Mathew.</p>
                     <p>It is verye neceſſarye alſo and profitable for the confirmacion &amp; ſtrengthening of our fayth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the moſt bleſſed ſacramente of the body and bloud of our ſauy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our chriſt which we ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ded to receaue in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his benefytes, that hereby, we may be truely ſertyfied in our conſcyence hys body to be geuen for vs, and his bloud to be ſhed for remiſſion of our ſynnes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Dethe</head>
                  <p>OF our fleſh &amp; fraill nature is ſo ferd &amp; abhorted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he approcheth, mans hert is filled and laden wyth ſuche ſorowes, panges, and anxieties as tong is
<pb facs="tcp:2714:20"/> not able to expreſſe.</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>¶ A medicine agaynſt the feare of death.</head>
                     <p>WE muſte call to our remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce deathe to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed and abolyſhed by Chryſt. So that nowe the ſoules of ſo many as truſt in Chriſt, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not dy nor peryſhe: but departynge from the body goeth ſtraight to Chryſt For thus was it ſayde to the thefe at his houre of death. Thys daye ſhalt thou be with me in paradiſe The bodye thoughe it reſte and pauſe for a whyle yet we be in cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine hope that at the laſte daye it ſhalbe rayſed againe to immortal and euerlaſting life. And therfore ſcripture calleth the deathe of the body but a ſlepe, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys ſame frayle, weke, vyle, mortall and cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruptible bodye, whych we cary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, which lieth ſicke &amp; ſore diſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, which ſhortly ſhalbe put into
<pb facs="tcp:2714:20"/> the earth, burne to aſſhes, deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beſtes or fooles, drowned in water, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſelf bodi (I ſay) ſhal be raiſed again incorruptible, glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious, bewtifull, ſtronge, pure im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall to poſſeſſe a newe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng lyfe:<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv</note> where there ſhall neither be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, thirſt, heate cold, ſynne, deth nor any kynde of cala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitie, but iuſtice, innocencye, lyfe, ioye bleſſe, world withoute ende. For as the body of Chryſt laid in the graue roſe agayne the thirde day neuer more to dye, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſhal the bodies of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleue in chryſt at the latter day be reſuſcitate to a lyfe, after whiche ſhall folowe no death. God who is of infinite po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and infallible truth hath pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſed theſe thynges, they muſte therfore nedes be ſo. And here it ſhalbe profitable to call to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce ſuche places of ſcrypture
<pb facs="tcp:2714:21"/> as treateth of the reſurrectyon of the fleſh, which be the words not of man but of god, who is able &amp; will certeynly fulfill what ſoeuer he hath ſpoken. No man can chaunge his wil, no man can alter his purpoſe. No creature can fru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrate let or tary his ſentence. He is omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he is true, he is faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, his goodnes and mercye is inexpicable. Let no man therfore doubte of the trueth of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des let no man doubte of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this promiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>☞ Here after foloweth certayne places of ſcripture witneſſing the reſurrection of the dead accordynge to the article of oure fayth wherin we ſay we beleue that this fleſh ſhal riſe agayne.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ioan, vi</note>THis is the wyl of my father which ſent me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſoeuer ſeith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; beleueth in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal haue life euer laſtinge and I
<pb facs="tcp:2714:21"/> wyl raiſe him vp again in the laſt daye.<note place="margin">Iohan. v</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The houre cometh wherin all they that be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the graues ſhal here the voice of the ſonne of god and ſhall go forth thei that haue done good vnto the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lyfe. For if ſo be that the ſpirite of him which rayſed vp Ieſus from the deade dwell in you:<note place="margin">Rom. vi.i.</note> euen he that rayſed vp Ieſus Chryſt from the dead ſhall alſo quicken your mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall bodies becauſe of hys ſpiryte that dwelleth in you.<note place="margin">i. Cor. vi</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>God hathe both rayſed vp oure Lord Ieſus Chriſt and ſhal alſo raiſe vs vp by his power.<note place="margin">Iohan. xi</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſte ſayeth Lazarus was but a ſlepe where in verye dede he was dead and buried. But Chriſt is the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and lyfe (as it is in the ſame place) ſo that he that beleueth on him thought he were
<pb facs="tcp:2714:22"/> dead he ſhall lyue, In verefienge whereof he raiſed ſtrayghte waye Lazarus being foure dayes dead and ſtynkynge. And becauſe we be naturallye in the agonye of deathe virye fearefull, weake and faintherted: to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we myght be the eaſelier perſwaded in the ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticle of reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Scripture ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth mencion of manye whiche in the tyme of the prophetes Chryſte and thappoſtles were called from death to lyfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Luc. vii Luc. i.</note>Chriſt rayſed the widowes ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne</p>
                     <p>He raiſed the ruler of the ſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goge his daughter.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iohan. xi Act. ix</note>He raiſed Lazarus.</p>
                     <p>Peter reſtored to life Tabitha.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Act. xx 4. Reg. iiii.</note>Paule raiſed again Eutichus</p>
                     <p>Elizeus the prophete called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to lyfe his hoſtes ſonne</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">4, Re. xvii.</note>Helias raiſed the babe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man of Sareptanie.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2714:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p>God toke alſo vnto him out of this frail and tranſitory life,<note place="margin">Gen. v. 4. Reg. ii.</note> theſe two excellent and holy men enoch and Helias quicke bothe bodye &amp; ſoule, to giue vs (as it were) a taſt and repreſentation of the true life to come, leſt after the opinion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ethnickes and epicures we ſhulde thynke there were no worlde, nor beinge after this wretched &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable lyfe. Let vs not forget what chriſt Ieſus lorde of lyfe, &amp; death, ſayth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .viii. of Luke, wepe not the maid is not dead but a ſlepe. Reaſon not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of god, nether perceiuing his pooer doth laugh this ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to ſcor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, but criſt proueth his ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g true, he raiſeth by &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead maide to lyfe. The .xv. chapter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Corin. is repleniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt godly pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and pithy conſolacions. Trulye it is more
<pb facs="tcp:2714:23"/> precious than any golde. For in that Chapit. ſaincte Paule dothe ſo annexe and couple oure reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reccion to the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſt as though thei coulde in no wyſe be ſeperate or deuyded after thys forme. Chryſt is ryſen from death (which thing is certen) ergo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhal vndoutedly riſe. For chriſt is our head and we his membres: Thys head is nether without, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyll forſake his membres. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it foloweth that where chriſt is, there ſhall we be. For why, we are the members of hys body and euen of his fleſhe and bone,<note place="margin">Ephe. v</note> what tonge, what penne, what wytte is able to ſet forthe (as it is worthy) this ineffable, &amp; ineſtimable glory of the mercye and grace of god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God hathe vouchſafe ſo lowe to humble himſelf as to become mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal man that this feble and fraile
<pb facs="tcp:2714:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> nature or man vnited and knit to the diuine natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> by the power &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fficacie of the godhead, myght be in haunced &amp; promoted to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. For trulye the nature of al faythfull men whyche, ether were before chryſt hath be ſens, at now or ſhalbe to the worldes ende: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedlie in chryſt very god and man hath optained immortallity The conſolacion therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riſeth of chriſtes reſurrection is of great efficacitie. As when ſainct Paule ſaythe to the Corinthians:<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv.</note> Chriſt is riſen againe from dead, and is the firſte fruictes of theim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſlepe for by one man truly cam death &amp; bi one man cometh the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. And as al die in Adame euyn ſo ſhall all be made alyue in chryſt but euery one in his order. The firſt is chriſt. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei which are chriſtes whych hathe beleued
<pb facs="tcp:2714:24"/> in his comming. And ſaint Paul dothe adde a ſimilitude taken of naturall thynges wherby he doth ſet forthe and declare the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of bodies. The ſymilitude is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſede whych is caſt into the earthe by the huſbandman dieth as it were and rotteth. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the leſſe it is not vtterlye loſte but at lenght ſpryngeth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth forthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, goodlye, beauty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful &amp; pleaſaunte. So our bodyes ſhall riſe agayne not feble, vyle, corruptyble, mortall: but ſtronge glorious incorruptible, immortal neuer to dy again but euer to liue</p>
                     <p>The wai into true and euerla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtynge lyfe to our longe home, as they call it, and contrey is by cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall death. Fleſhe and blood be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge corruptible and mortall can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not inherit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kydgdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god wher nothing is but life. Therfore this
<pb facs="tcp:2714:24"/> corruptible bodi muſt put on i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Oze. xiiii. Eſa. xxv,</note> &amp; this mortal muſt put on immortality. Than ſhal the ſaing that is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be fulfilled, Death is ſwalowed vp in victory. They that beleue in Chryſte hath nowe ouercommed ſynne, deathe, and hel. Therfore not fearinge deathe but ſtronge, hold, and well harted in Chryſte: they maye ſaye deathe where is thy ſting? death where is thy victorye? The ſtinge of death is ſynne, and the power of ſynne is the lawe. But thankes be vnto God whiche hathe geauen vs the victorye through our lord Ieſus Chryſte.</p>
                     <p>Let vs heare alſo more ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces full of godly and mightye conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion.</p>
                     <p>He that hath raiſed vp Ieſus ſhal rayſe vs vp alſo with Ieſus<note place="margin">ii. Cor iiii</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:2714:25"/> Our conuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acion is in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence we do loke for the ſauiour our lord Ieſus chriſt which ſhall chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge our vile body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be like faſhioned vnto hys glorious body accordyng to the workynge of his power,<note place="margin">Philli. iiii</note> by the which alſo he is able to ſubdue al thinges vnto him ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Ye are dead and your life is hid with chriſt in god,<note place="margin">Col. iii.</note> but when chriſt your life ſhal appere then ſhall ye alſo appere in glory with him.</p>
                     <p>We wolde not brethern) that ye ſhuld be ignorant concerninge them that ſlepe,<note place="margin">i. Teſſ. iiii</note> that ye ſorow not alſo as other do whyche haue no hope. For if we beleue that Ieſus chryſt died and roſe agayne: euen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo which are a ſlepe through Ieſus ſhal god bringe with him.</p>
                     <p>Saynct Paule alſo doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort Timoth<note place="margin">ii. Tim. ii.</note> with the article of
<pb facs="tcp:2714:25"/> reſurrection ſayng. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>membre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the lord Ieſus Chriſte beyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he ſede of Dauid roſe again from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead according to my goſpell. And if we be deade with hym we ſhal alſo lyue with him. If we ſuffer pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly we ſhal alſo raign with him.</p>
                     <p>It was written alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hebrus<note place="margin">Heb. ii</note> that Chryſte taſted deathe for all men, and that he was partaker of fleſhe and bloude .i. became ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he mighte deſtroye hym which had the rule of death (that is) the deuell, and that he myghte delyuer them which were in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage al th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ir lyfe time by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the feare of death.</p>
                     <p>God hath delyuered vs,<note place="margin">ii. Tim. i</note> and called vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an holy calling not according to our workes but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his purpoſe and grace whyche is geauen vs in Chryſte
<pb facs="tcp:2714:26"/> Ieſu before the time of the world but is now made manifeſt by the apperinge of oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt which truly hath deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed deathe and hath broughte lyfe and immortalite to lyghte, by the goſpell.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Ioh. iii</note>We know that we are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from lyfe to deathe becauſe we loue the bretherne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iohn. 41</note>In this hathe the loue of god appered in vs, becauſe god ſente his onely begotten ſonne into the world y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we mighte lyue through him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. xix</note>I knowe that my redem er doth lyue, and in the laſt daye I ſhall ryſe agayne, and agayne be wrapped in my owne ſkine. And in my owne fleſhe ſhall ſee God, whome I my ſelfe ſhall ſe &amp; theſe my eyes ſhall beholde and none othere</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2714:26"/>
                     <p>Theſe places of holye ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſuche lyke, yf we diligent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre &amp; faythfully imbrace: we ſhall perceaue greaet conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and conforte And euen wyth ſayncte Paule reioyſe,<note place="margin">Phil. iii.</note> that we knowe Chryſte and the power of his reſurrectyon, wherby death is ouercomed. Nether is there nowe (to theſe that beleue in Chriſt) any thynge in deathe terrible or to be feared, ſauinge onlye the Image and outwarde forme, hurte it can not. Lyke as a dede ſerpente kea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth ſtil his old fearefull ſhape &amp; forme: but to ſtynge or do harme he hathe no power at al. And lyke as by the braſin ſerpente whyche Moyſes by goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente ſette vp in deſerte when it was loked vpon through the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of goddes woorde men were delyuered from<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> daunger of the
<pb facs="tcp:2714:27"/> lyuelye and venyme ſerpentes ſo our deathe is made harmles and we deliuered frome the feare and daunger of it, ſo ofte as wyth the eyes of our faythe we do beholde the helthefull and medycynable dethe of Chryſt. In concluſion deathe is nowe become but a I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and ſhadowe of deathe, yea the entrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and gate to lyfe. For Chriſt who is trueth it ſelf ſayth, Yf anye man kepe my worde,<note place="margin">Iob. viii.</note> he ſhall neuer ſee death, For a man truſtynge to the mercye of God, through faithe, whiche he concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uith by herynge of Chryſtes goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: is ſo vnite and knyt to chriſt his lord and mayſter, that he can not be plucked nor ſeperate frome hym.</p>
                     <p>The bodye in dede for a tyme is ſeperate from the ſoule but in certayne hope of riſinge agayn to
<pb facs="tcp:2714:27"/> euerlaſtinge lyfe. And ſo he that beleuethe in Chryſt dothe not ſee nor fele the euerlaſtinge dethe of body and ſoule, which is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting dampnacion, For the death of good men is nothynge els but a departure from thys tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and mortal life: to immortality to chryſt, to hys angelles and ſainctes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Hell and dampnacion.</head>
                  <p>DOth offer it ſelf at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hour of death, ſo that many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes man doth greatli feare leſt he be abiecte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fauour of god &amp; appoynted to euerlaſtynge payne
<pb facs="tcp:2714:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> The deuyll (whyche ſeketh by al meanes howe to deuoure vs) ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge vp in youre myndes manye daungerous &amp; troubellous thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes concernyng our electyon &amp; predeſtinacion.</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>¶ A medicine againſt the feare of hell and dampnacion.</head>
                     <p>WHen the deuil goeth about to cauſe vs to dyſpaire or to doubt of our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whether we be of the numbre of them that are appointed to euerlaſtyng lyfe or no, In any wayes let vs not be to boulde in copynge wyth hym, let vs not enter dyſputacyon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte hym (for he is to ſubtyle and expert for vs) but ſay ſhortly vnto him. Away Satan with ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe, it is written, thou ſhalte not tempt the lord thy God. For ſeing that god as a moſt louyng father
<pb facs="tcp:2714:28"/> hathe not onlye geauen vs lyfe. fedde and preſeruyd vs, to thys houre: but alſo hathe indued and euen loden vs from tyme to tyme with hys ſinguler benefites, what madnes were it contrary to oure former experyence, nowe to doubt of his mercy? He hathe receauyd vs into hys flocke by baptime. He hathe ſente vs the Goſpell of hys grace, wherein he hathe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed to become oure father. We haue he fedde wyth the fleſhe and bloude of hys ſonne oure ſauiour CHRISTE in remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce that oure debtes be payd and we acquyted, whye ſhoulde we nowe then doubte of the good wyl of GOD towarde vs? lette vs not therfore admytte the dout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and daungerous Imagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyons of oure predeſtinacion
<pb facs="tcp:2714:29"/> which the deuell like a crafty and malicious marchaunt doth labor to iuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. But let vs thinke vpon ſuche ſentences as God woulde haue our mindes occupied wyth all, whych Chriſte hym ſelfe hath preſcribed, as Iohn. iii, where he ſayethe. GOD hathe ſo loued the woorlde, that he hathe geuen his onelye begotten Sonne that who ſo euer beleueth in him ſhall nor periſhe, but haue lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtynge. Loo here we ſee that he which beleueth in Chryſt, which faythfully acknowlegeth chryſte to be his ſanctificacyon, iuſtyce redempcyon and ſatiſfaccion: can not be dampned, but is aſſured of euerlaſting lyfe. So many as conceaue faythe by bearynge of Goddes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ord: and ſo truſte ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly vpon the mercy of chryſte Vndoutedlye they be of the num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:2714:29"/> of thoſe whych be choſen to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſtyng blyſſe, knowen before in CHRISTE predeſtinate. and written long ſyth in the boke of lyfe. Theſe thynges be mooſte certayne and moſt true, God can neyther deceyue nor be deceaued.<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> Such is hys good wyll, ſo hathe he purpoſed and decreed afore the worlde beganne, what thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſo euer therefore oure enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my the deuell (ſpytinge oure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, and ſekynge our deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon) ſhall put in our minde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this doctrine. Lette them not moue vs, lett them not make vs afrayde, but lette vs truſt tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in chriſte: and ſo ſhall he be come oures, and we become hys, who beynge our good LORD, we can mot periſhe nor be damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.<note place="margin">Io. x</note> For he wyl loſe none of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:2714:30"/> that hys father hathe geuen hym, we muſte fyxe oure eyes vppon Chryſte, we muſte flee to hym, we muſte cleaue to hym. He is oure onelye and true ſauyoure, who muſte be apprehended and imbraced by faythe, yf we loke to be ſaued. For they that beleue ryghtelye in Chryſte they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate to euerlaſtynge lyfe. Here we muſte diligently remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre and earneſtelye expende the godly exhortacion of ſaynt Paul whych he writeth in the .xii. to the Hebrewes, whoſe wordes be theſe Lette vs runne by pacyence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the battell that is ſette afore vs,<note place="margin">He. xii.</note> lokynge vnto Ieſus, the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore and finiſher of fayth, whyche when the ioye was ſet afore hym, ſuffered the croſſe, and dyſpyſed the ſhame, and ſitteth at the ryght hand of the ſeate of God.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2714:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p>Furthermore all the greuous temtacyons and afflictyons that Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yſte ſuffered, he ſufferyd them for our ſakes.<note place="margin">Heb. iiii</note> As ſaincte Paule ſayth alſo in the .iiii. to the hebrus we haue not a highe prieſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not able to haue compaſſyon on oure weakenes: but ſuch one was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd in all pointes wythout ſynne let vs therfore wyth bouldnes go vnto the ſeat of hys grace, that we may o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tayne mercye and fynde grace to helpe in tyme of nede Let vs in any ways conſider and deplye imprinte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our harts, chriſt to be geuin vnto vs, not onlye to thend y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might be redemid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled &amp; made partakers of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him we myght haue an example, bothe howe to liue, and alſo how to end oure lyfe. Nether can anye man
<pb facs="tcp:2714:31"/> liue, ſuffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r or dye well: vnles he loke vpon and folowe the lyfe, ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rynge and death of Chryſt, if therfore we deſire to end thys lyfe well and godlye: let vs conſider and remembre howe Chryſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued him ſelfe in that bitter and ſmarte agonye, when hangyng vpon the croſſe, he was aſſaulted with diuers fyerſſe and moſt gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous temtacyons, and praye that we may haue grace to folowe hys example.</p>
                     <p>FIrſt he was temptyd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſyn whan being ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged betwixte two theues as a notable and hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſynner: it was ſayd vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf thou beiſt the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>at. xxvii.</note> come downe from the croſſe. By this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelious voyce what do they ſignifye elles, but that they iudged hym a noughtie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
<pb facs="tcp:2714:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> perſon, ſuch one as by craft ſubtiltye, falſheade, ſoſſerye, and other vnlawfull meanes had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued the people, hadde blynded the worlde, and to be nothynge leſſe then the ſonne of GOD.</p>
                     <p>Euen in lyke maner at the houre of deathe doth the deuyll tempte man, what ſoeuer man hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſte god, al the ſinnes that euer he dyd, he ſheweth vnto hym, he doth exaggerate them to the vttermoſte, to thende that the multitude and hainouſnes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſidered and perceaued manne ſhulde doubte of the mercye and fauoure of god, and, ſo fall into deſperacion. Here we had nede to ſtande ſure. And euery one of vs had nede to aunſwer our enemye, thus temptinge vs after thys ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner I knowledge mi ſelfe to haue ſynnes aboue all numbre, and
<pb facs="tcp:2714:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> meaſure but Chryſte, who neuer ſinned in whoſe mouth was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no guile, who is that verye inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent lambe, hathe ſuffered deathe for my ſynnes, he hathe waſſhed them awaye, he hathe ſatyſfied aboundantlye for them,<note place="margin">Eſay. iiii.</note> howe ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye and howe greate ſo euer they were, Chriſtes deathe partayneth alſo to me he was wounded alſo for my iniquities, he was bruſed for my vngracyouſenes, by hys ſtrypes I am alſo healed. All my ſynnes hath Chryſte taken to him ſelfe, ſo that nowe I haue none (thankes be to CHRIST) who hathe ſatyſfyed for theym in hys owne body.</p>
                     <p>CHRIST was tempted al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> death, when it was ſaid vnto hym:<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>7.</note> he hathe ſaued other, but he canne not ſaue hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe.
<pb facs="tcp:2714:32"/> (As thought it ſhoulde be ſayd he) is nowe at appoynte, he muſt dye, there is no remedye, he canne not eſcape. Thus dothe oure olde and erreconcyble enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my labour to feare vs wyth deth but let vs holde out the buckeler of faythe in Chryſt agaynſt hym Lette vs remembre that Chryſte our Lord, kynge of glorye, and prynce of lyfe, coulde not be ouer commed nor holden of death, but thoughe he once taſted of deathe: he nowe liueth and raygneth for euer. Thys lorde of oures will not leaue vs, nor ſuffer deathe to execute any tyranny agaynſt vs, that after he hath ſuffered vs to be tempted a whyle he wyll alſo that we dye corporally: al that is wholy for our welth.</p>
                     <p>Neyther coulde we other wayes
<pb facs="tcp:2714:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> come to euerlaſtynge lyfe but by temporall death. We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore leaue this preſent lyfe ere we can inherite the eternall life. Alſo thys corporall deathe bringethe thys comoditie that by taſtynge the bitternes and ſowernes of it: we haue experyence and knowe the excedynge loue that Chryſte bare towarde vs, and the ineſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le benefite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did for vs in clenſyng our ſynnes, in abolyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge of death, in breakinge vp of hel gates, and al by his death.</p>
                     <p>Other wayes we could neuer haue knowen the power of chryſt in aboliſhing of deathe, we could neuer haue iuſtly eſtemed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of thes benefit, we could neuer haue ſene howe iuſte cauſe we haue to geue thanks to chriſt our Lord and redeamer. Chryſte lyuing trulye, we ſhall alſo lyue.
<pb facs="tcp:2714:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> and this corporal deth to vs ſhall be nothynge els but a ſwete and holſome ſlepe, an intraunce and gate into the true &amp; bleſſed lyfe. For after thys tranſitory lyfe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begynne we fyrſt truly to lyue.</p>
                     <p>THirdli chriſt was tempted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hel, or euerlaſtynge da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was ſaid vnto him he hath truſted in GOD let him, now delyuer hym yf he wyll. As thoughe they ſhould ſaye. Nowe it appearethe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hathe hoped in God in vayne. For god wyl none of hym, he hathe forſaken hym, he likethe hym not, he dothe abhorre hym, he wyll caſte hym downe to hel &amp; perpetually co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne hym. When therfore the temptor ſhall laſche at vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e temptacyons, we maye not ſhrinke, we may not
<pb facs="tcp:2714:34"/> be afraid, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> may not be dyſcora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend our ſelf, wholy to CHRISTE, hange vpon hym who is wholye oures, who hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelf wholy to vs, ſo that ſynne, deathe, nor hel, hath no thynge to do wyth vs. Chryſte with a ineſtimable price, his owne bloude hathe deliueryd vs frome the tyranny of the deuyl, and euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſtinge dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is become our innocency, our lyfe, and oure iuſtice. Let vs take hede in anye ways that we turne not our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes from CHRISTE, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed. Yf we cleue to hym, we are ſet vpon a ſure and inexpugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rocke, agaynſte the whyche all the power of hell is able to do nothinge. So that we may boldli exclame, and euery one ſaye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>th
<pb facs="tcp:2714:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> CHRISTE I prouided the lorde afore my eys all waye,<note place="margin">Pſal. xvi</note> for he is at my ryght elbowe, that I ſhulde not be mouyd, therefore my harte hath be gladde and my tonge hathe reioyſed, moreouer my fleſſhe ſhall reſte in hope. By faythe in CHRISTE we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſonnes of GOD, the bretherne and coheires of Chryſt, and partakers of euerlaſtynge lyfe, by this faith departing hence we ſhall go to the kyngdome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paryd for the electe, afore the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnynge of the world. And if in the feruentnes of theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s our faythe begine to wauer yf we do not bere pacyentlye the wyll of oure heuinlye Father, if our loue towarde god waxe faynt and cold yf o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> hope beginne to be feble &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2714:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> weake: and therfore we begynne to feare, leſſe god and we be not all at a full poynt, but that he is yet deſpleſed with vs (which ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion ſurely is verye greuous painful, dangerous, and hard to ouercome) we muſt cal to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance Chriſt to haue ſuffred for vs ſo intollerable and inuincible tentacions: that there apered no help, no confort, no refuge, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in GOD and the whole worlde: ſemyd to haue for ſaken him, and to be againſt him: In ſo mouche that he exclamed, O mi god, o mi GOD why haſte thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me. Oh here was a greuous tentacion. A ſharpe and a bytter deathe that CHRSTE ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for vs, and all to make the way of the croſſe and death eaſy vnto vs. Therfore ſeynge that,
<pb facs="tcp:2714:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> CHRISTE of hys owne free wyll, caſte hym ſelfe in to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of intollerable payne, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ty, and anxeity (GOD our moſt louynge Father beyng ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with contente) vndoubtedlye he knoweth and conſidereth our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmite, vndoubtedly he will not deale with vs accordynge to the rigour of the lawe, but will bere much with vs and pardon many thinges to our infirmity. Dothe not CHRIST ſpeake to all men? doth he not call men, when he ſayth: Come vnto me all you that do labour and are laden and I ſhal refreſh you? how can ther be any greater conſolacyon? how coulde CHRISTE ſpeake more mercyfull to vs. There be many thinges that pynche<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vexe, and trouble man greuouſly: but
<pb facs="tcp:2714:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> what thyng is it that can trouble the conſcience of a ſynner, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doubteth of the mercy of god, then whan he feareth leſt God will caſt him of then whan he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not perſuad him ſelf to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ani truſt of gods m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rci but Imagine that us withered mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he ſhall cut of and caſt away. Here we had nede of chriſts preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t helpe, here we had nede of ſpedi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, leſt this violente tempeſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelme and drowne vs. But let vs not feare. CHRISTE is no decembler, he wyll ſtande by his worde, he wyll perfourme hys promiſe, He wyll helpe and refreſhe Therefore when we begynne to trimble and feare in our conſcience, when we beginne to doubt of goddes mercy, when
<pb facs="tcp:2714:36"/> we perceaue our faythe to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Let vs forthwith call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon GOD, and that feruentlye, and that indeſinantlye, euen from the bottome of oure harte, that he tourne not his face from vs.</p>
                     <p>Lette vs power be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ore hym all that dothe trouble vs. Let vs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe to hym oure meſerye, oure imbecillitye, oure incredulity. Let vs crye wyth the diſciples, Lorde increaſe oure fayth. And wyth the Father of the Lunatycke,<note place="margin">Luc. xvii.</note> Lorde we beleue, helpe our incredulyte. And w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prophet.<note place="margin">Marci. i</note> Lorde make haſte to help vs. For thy mercy is aboue all thy workes. O mooſte louyng, O moſte mercyful father lord god of our healthe,<note place="margin">Pſa. lxi</note> our onlye helpe and refuge. Enter not into iudgemente with thy ſeruauntes.
<pb facs="tcp:2714:37"/> Chryſte is our iuſtyce oure redep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, he for vs hath ſuffered moſt bitter &amp; cruel death.</p>
                     <p>Let theſe thynges moue the o father of mercy. For this thi ſon our ſauior chryſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s ſake haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, confirme and ſtrength our harte in fayth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort vs with the conſolacions of thy holy ſpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, that we may finally optayne Ioy euerlaſtyng, through Ieſus chriſt Amen,</p>
                     <p>After thys ſort yf we (laboryng wreſting and ſtryuinge wyth our imbecillyty, accuſing afore god, &amp; lamentinge our puſilianitye and incredulity) do catch hold of chriſt and clene faſt to hym, earneſtlye and feruently deſiryng hys help, that he wyl vouchſafe to take our place &amp; to ſupplye that is lackyng
<pb facs="tcp:2714:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> in vs. Theſe thinges if we do, ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly all thinges ſhalbe well, we ſhal auoyde and eſcape eaſly al daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; peril, we ſhalbe ſafe inough For theſe two, to beleue in Chryſt and with hart to deſire fayth, doth not much differ the one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For though we fele yet great weaknes and imperfection in our ſelfe yet this ought to comfort vs that god willeth &amp; commaundeth that he ſhoulde be called vpon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath promiſed to here and help theſe, that cal ryghtly vpon hym. Now as nothing is more iuſtli or neceſſarily deſyred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true fayth, euen ſo god hearyth no prayer ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or more gladly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan man findyng no goodnes in hym ſelfe, doth acknowlege his owne infyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, hys owne myſery, hys owne beggerlines, dothe accuſe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:2714:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> his owne increduliti, &amp; with depe ſighes, &amp; harti deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>res calleth for fayth. Theſe ſighes, theſe deſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, theſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ayers, this litil ſparke of faithe is the very ſede of God, wrought in vs by him which ſaith of chryſte by the Prophet Eſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhall not quenche the ſmoking filaxe, nor breake the bruſyd rede, Therfore let vs ſtedfaſtly beleue, or at the leaſte earneſtelye and hartely pray that we maye beleue, bewayling afore god our lacke of fayth, whiche thinges if we do, we nede not doubt bot we be acceptid of god, we be taken for his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> For it is not for noughte, nor in vayne that he hathe layde oure imbecillitie and ſynnes vpon hys only begoten ſonnes backe.</p>
                     <p>In Mathew<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> it is ſaid bleſſed be thoſe that mourne, for thei ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:2714:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> comforted, bleſſed be thoſe that ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger after righteouſnes, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey ſhalbe ſatiſfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d. Theſe wordes ar ſpok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n alſo to vs, they may iuſtly be applied to vs, we mourne and are ſorye in our hartes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we haue miſpendid our life paſt. We wiſh and deſire, yea we euen honger &amp; thirſt after righteouſnes. Let vs be of good chere, we ſhall o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tain our deſyre, we ſhalbe comforted we ſhalbe counted iuſt afore god for Chryſt our ſauioure his ſake. Finally let vs after this example of Chryſt and ſainct Steuen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend our ſoules into the handes of god your heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, ſayng euery one after this maner.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> Moſt merciful father I com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend into thy holye handes my
<pb facs="tcp:2714:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpirit, yea thy ſpirit, for thou haſt creat it, thou haſte commytted it for a tyme to the body, thou haſt geuen it thy owne Image and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylitude. Thou haſt ſente for the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption of it, thi owne moſt dere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly belouyd ſonne to ſhed his bloud. Thys the ſpirite, I reſigne into thi han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, O GOD of all mercye, I am thyne al that I am, I be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeche the refuſe not thy owne, but receaue, kepe and place me in euerlaſting glory for the ſake of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, thy only begotten ſonne Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:2714:39"/>
            <head>¶ A prayer to be ſayde at the houre of death.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Lorde Ieſu, whych art the onely health of al menne li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge and the euerlaſtynge lyfe of them whyche dye in thy fayth: I wretched ſynner geue and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelfe wholy vnto thy moſt bleſſed will. And I beynge ſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the thynge cannot peryſhe whych is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted vnto thy mercy: wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly nowe I leaue thys frayle and wycked fleſhe, in hope of the reſurreccion, which in better wyſe ſhal reſtore it to me againe. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the moſt mercyful lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chryſt that thou wylte by thy grace: make ſtronge my ſoule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt all temptacyons and that thou wylte couer and defende me wyth the buckler of thy mercye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſaultes of the deuyl
<pb facs="tcp:2714:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> I ſe and knowledge that there is in my ſelfe no helpe of ſaluacion, but al my confidence hope, &amp; truſt is in thy mooſte mercyful good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> haue no merytes nor good workes which I maye all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the: Of ſinnes &amp; euyl workes alas &amp; ſee a great heape: but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe thy mercy, I truſte to bee in the numbre of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to whom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou wylt not impute theyr ſinnes, but take and accept me for ryghteous and iuſt, &amp; to be thinheritour of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtynge lyfe. Thou mercyful Lord werte borne for my ſak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dyddeſt ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bothe hungre and truſt for my ſake, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dydeſt preache and teache thou didſt pray &amp; faſte for my ſake thou diddeſt all good woorkes and dedes for my ſake, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſufferedeſt moſt greuous paines and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes for my ſake: And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally thou gaueſt thy moſte precy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:2714:40"/> body to dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and thy bloud to be ſhed on the croſſe for my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake. Now<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mooſt mercyfull ſauyour, let all theſe thynges profyte me, whyche thou freely, haſte geuen me, that haſte geuen thy ſelfe for me: let thy bloude cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, &amp; waſhe awaye the ſpottes and foulneſſe of my ſynnes, Lette thy ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe hyde and couer myne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghteouſneſſe. Lette the merytes of thy paſſyon and bloude, be the ſatiſfaccion of my ſynnes. Geue me Lord thy grace, that my faythe and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thy bloud, wauer not in me, but euer be fyrme and conſtante, that the hope of thy mercy, and lyfe euerlaſtynge, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer decaye in me, that charytye ware not colde in me: fynallye, that the weakeneſſe of my fleſhe be not ouercome wyth the feare of death. Graunte me mercyfull
<pb facs="tcp:2714:41"/> ſauioure, that when deathe hath ſhutte vp the eyes of my bodye, yet that the eyes of my ſoule maye ſtyll beholde and loke vpon thee, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death hath taken awaye the vſe of my tonge and ſpeache, yet that my harte may crye &amp; ſaye vnto the In man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s tuas domine commendo ſpiritum meum: that is to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y: O lord into thy handes I g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue and commytte my ſoule. Domine Ieſu accipe ſpiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um. Lorde Ieſu receiue my ſoule vnto thee Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London by Wyllyam Copland, for Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Kele.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2714:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
